Guide to the Wallace Thurman Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Wallace Thurman Collection
1927-1942
JWJ MSS 12
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(4 boxes)
The Wallace Thurman Collection contains Correspondence, (including letters from Langston Hughes), Writings, primarily versions of Aunt Hagar's Children and the musical play Harlem, written with William Jourdan Rapp, and Personal Papers.
Thurman, Wallace, 1902-1934
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Wallace Thurman Collection contains items presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection after his death in 1934, many from Mrs. William Jourdan Rapp, the widow of Thurman's collaborator on "Harlem."
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WALLACE THURMAN (1902-1934)
Wallace Thurman was a novelist and playwright who found fame before his early death with the novel The Blacker the Berry and the play, "Harlem". A biographical sketch of Thurman written by Harold Jackman, can be found in folder 59 of this collection.
Scope and Contents
NOTE: This finding aid was produced from a previously existing manuscripts inventory. All pertinent information has been retained.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Rapp, William Jourdan, 1895-1942; Thurman, Wallace, 1902-1934
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Letters
    - Grant, Helen from City Hospital, 1934 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      To: 1 / From: 0
    - Harris, Robert, 1929 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1929, 1932, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      To: 6 / From: 0
    - Jackman, Harold, 1928-34, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      To: 0 / From: 4
    - Jackman, Harold, 1941-48 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      letters from Jackman to Carl
      Van Vechten re: Thurman
      Collection
      4 letters
    - Rapp, Paul, 1928 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      letter to William Jourdan Rapp
      1 letter
    - Rapp, William Jourdan, 1928, 1929, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      To: 0 / From: 25
    - Rapp, Mrs. William Jourdan, 1942, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      letters to Carl Van Vechten
      2 letters
- Writings, Series II
  - Aunt Hagar's Children
    - Draft, typescript and carbon and printed version, corrected (Box 1, Folder 10-15)
      Includes: Table of Contents, Author's Preface,
      "Notes on a Step-child" autobiographical
      statement
      "This Negro Literary Renaissance"
      "Tribute"
      "Mr. Van Vechten's Jurors"
      "Frederick Douglass"
      "Booker T. Washington"
      "Marcus Garvey"
      "Draw Your Own Conclusions"
      "The Perpetual Bugaboo"
      "The Coming Revolution"
      "So This Is Harlem"
      "Terpsichore in Harlem"
  - "Harlem" (written with William Jourdan Rapp)
    - "Cordelia the Crude," scenario of "Harlem", typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Cordelia the Crude," printed version, Fire!! A Quarterly Devoted to the Younger Negro Artists, Vol. 1, no. 1, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Color Parade", title pages and synopsis of early version of "Harlem", holograph and typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Untitled, early versions of "Harlem", holograph, typescript, and carbon, corrected (Box 1, Folder 19-24)
    - "City of Refuge", early version of "Harlem", holograph, typescript, and carbon, corrected (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    - "Black Mecca", early version of "Harlem" typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Black Belt", early version of "Harlem", typescript carbon (3 copies), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
    - Assorted revised pages of "Harlem", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32-34)
    - [EMPTY FOLDERS] (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - Clippings re: "Harlem", 1929 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
    - Playbills, theater magazines and advertisements re: "Harlem", 1929 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Contract for Crosby Gaige to produce "Black Mecca", 1928 Jan 9 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Articles about "Harlem" and life in Harlem
    - "Harlem", article about play by Thurman and Rapp, printed version, Detroit Free Press, 1929 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "The Writing of 'Harlem', the Story of a Strange Collaboration" by W. J. Rapp, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "'Harlem' as Educational Drama," by Thurman and Rapp, holograph and typescript of article (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Articles about the production of "Harlem", holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Includes:"Casting and Directing
      Harlem
      Untitled article by Wallace Thurman
      "How 'Harlem' Got to Broadway" by
      W. J. Rapp
      "My Collaboration" by Wallace Thurman
    - "Two Playwrights Look at Harlem" by W. J. Rapp, holograph and typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "What's Happening in the Black Belt", by Thurman and Rapp, holograph, typescripts and carbon, corrected, and printed version (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "Few Know Real Harlem, the City of Surprises" by Thurman and Rapp, typescripts, corrected and printed version, [1929] (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Harlem House-Rent Parties", one version by Wallace Thurman, one version by W. J. Rapp, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "Sweetbacks" by W. J. Rapp, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Untitled article re: dance called "The Bump," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Harlemese" and "Glossary of Harlemisms" by Wallace Thurman and W. J. Rapp, holographs (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "A Lady: Past Revolution, in Memoriam: Circa 1936", poem, holograph (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "Negro Artists and the Negro," article, printed version, The New Republic ", 1927 Aug 31 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Nephews of Uncle Remus", article, printed version, The Independent, 1927 Sep 24 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Review of Langston Hughes; Not Without Laughter, printed version, New York Evening Post, 1938 Jul 28 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Untitled autobiographical statement, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Untitled poem fragment, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Untitled, four pages of handwritten manuscript about tubercular patients, ca. 1934 (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Personal Papers, 1934, 1942; Series III
  - Biographical sketches of Wallace Thurman by Harold Jackman and Hughes Allison, 1934, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Clippings, re: Wallace Thurman, 1935-35, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Untitled autobiographical statements by William Jourdan Rapp, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - William Jourdan Rapp, obituary and memorial address clippings, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Photographs: Wallace Thurman, William Jourdan Rapp, and Chester Erskin, 1941-42, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 4: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 8 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Box 1, folder 20 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Box 1, folder 21 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Box 3, folder 53 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Box 3, folder 54 (Box 4, Folder 69)